CROSSING THE LINE
Marcel ?
Oh, there you are. We've got problems
with the main circular saw.
Any news of Meyer ?
Meyers' in the Stalag.
His wife got a letter this morning.
That's the day shot. Ah well, too bad, call Berthier.
It'll be expensive, but too bad.
Inès, remember to call Berthier,
we've a problem with the saw again.
Very good, Monsieur Schwartz.
Monsieur Schwartz ?
Kommandant.
You make planks here, don't you ?
Yes, planks and everything made of wood.
I need planks and lots of beams.
For the extension of the barracks....the old boys school.
It's a rush job. Can you do it ?
I need the details of the order.
We've just had a problem with the saw...
A motorcyclist will bring you a file during the day.
I need a quick answer.
Obviously, this work will be paid for
in marks not francs.
Monsieur...
What do you think of it ?
You're the boss.
We can do it.
We'll need to find guys.
And there's the problem of delivery.
I suppose if we're working for the
Germans they'll cough up the petrol.
That's not a bad scam.
The foresters' delivery wagon. I'll get on it.
Look.
So, Te Quiero ?
You're giving Papa a little smile ?
He only smiles for Maman.
Are you coming to Papa ?
Here !
The bottle.
Commissaire de Kerven has asked a favour.
He has a problem lodging Inspecteur Marchetti.
You know, the young cop that helped us at the Church.
So ?
Well, I accepted him staying here, we've room.
You could have asked me first !
It's a bother ?
No, no.
You can leave it, Maria.
Monsieur le Maire, a German military
telephone cable was sabotaged last night...
... in the central square, just in front
of the school. It's intolerable.
I am sorry Kommandant.
You're not playing the game.
When I think of you pestering me with stories
of parcels for your POWs !
It happened last night ?
Just in front of the school.
There'll be an investigation by our Police.
Are you sure this is sabotage ?
Monsieur le Maire, be informed, that from today
until further notice, the curfew starts at 18:00h.
I won't have the time to warn people.
Henceforth you will establish a list
of the names, of 20 heads of family.
And personally bring this list to me
at the Kommandantur by tonight.
Otherwise... !
I haven't had the opportunity
to congratulate you on your nomination.
Cutting a German cable ! Who could
have done this stupidity ?
It's this list of 20 names that worries me.
You believe he wants to take hostages
for a thing like that ?
They're not going to take hostages
for a so-called cut cable.
If it hadn't been cut they wouldn't
be coming to crap all over us.
No. Above all the question is what to do.
I don't follow you clearly Monsieur le Sous-Préfet.
We could fix matters, if we arrest
the jerk who did this.
It's not for us to do the Boches' work !
Excuse me Commissaire, you didn't
exactly shine in June.
I don't think you're well placed
to give us moral lessons.
I had a moment of weakness. It happens.
Not when one is in charge of public order.
Messieurs !
Is it certain this would solve the blockage of POW parcels ?
Monsieur le Maire, if we start to do police work
to obtain something from the Boches, we're done for.
They'll end up asking us for anything they please.
Commissaire, he's asked for a list
for heaven's sake !
It's essential for rounding up hostages.
If something can be done to avoid it,
it must be done.
I'm not asking the impossible, but see
what you can get from your informers...
... in that neighbourhood, you never know.
Excuse me, I have to go.
A marriage and then a birth.
If we find the culprit, are you going
to hand him over to the Boches ?
Of course not !
If you find him, we'll brag to the Germans...
...and bring him before a French Court.
That way we win on all counts.
Don't miss this opportunity
to redeem yourself de Kervern.
I don't understand.
I'm supporting ten families here
and I have no priority !
I'm sorry, I really can't do anything for you.
Four soldier's death notices today.
If you really want to inform the families.
How are the interim arrangements going ?
Are they taking shape ?
As you can see, we're coping.
Good luck !
Good day Monsieur le Maire.
I have a real problem with petrol.
Ah, no, I've nothing to do with petrol.
The Germans control absolutely everything.
How am I going to run the sawmill without petrol ?
I'm sorry, I don't have good news.
I have a letter for the wife of your tenant, Lorrain Germain.
It's a form letter. They took their time !
Poor Marie !
It makes me sad. She's a good woman.
I'm going to inform her right now.
Why's he smiling at us like that ?
Because we're cops. The Germans love order.
Ah yes.
Sabotage as tourism, right ?
Yes.
The guy had to have pulled the cable from below.
You've seen the anchors...it needed a hell of a force.
Surely there were several of them.
Anyway !
To come into the courtyard of the school
during full curfew, with the sentries around....
So ?
It suggests a concerted plan, a real organisation.
I don't see who could do something like this so quickly.
Perhaps really the Communists.
That's your obsession, eh, the Communists ?
No. But I know they have the means and people.
For now the Communists go along with the Boches.
Why would they sabotage one of their cables ?
I know the Communists well, they only work for themselves !
And then I might track down Marcel Larcher.
The guy at the sawmill.
In 1936 he was fingered as a Communist.
And there  were the leaflets in June. Remember ?
Yes.
Marcel Larcher's also the Mayor's brother.
When are you moving in with him ?
Right away.
OK. For now we can put the Communists on one side.
I'm going to trawl through the school.
As soon as you've moved in, scout around.
See if anyone saw or heard anything last night.
Tomorrow, possible. Today, not possible !
Not valid. Not possible to cross the demarcation Line.
But how can it not be valid. Look at it
before saying it's not valid.
Not valid. Make a U-turn.
Listen, I'm sorry, this document is valid.
Look 15th of October. This is the 30th of September.
Today, problem. Make a U-turn.
Bettine ?... May I ?
Good day Monsieur Schwartz.
Good day. Do you know Marie Germain
in Les Essarts?
Good day Monsieur Schwartz.
Good day. Do you know Marie Germain
in Les Essarts?
Sort of.
Do me a great favour. Go and ask her to meet me here.
Tell her its urgent.
Good, OK.
Good of you. Thank you.
Very urgent, eh.
What is it ?
Its the list Von Ritter demanded.
Twenty men's names.
You put yourself down ?
Darling, as First Magistrate of the Commune,
I must be first on the list.
You haven't included your brother !
Yes, I was able to spare him that !
You know Micheline is very sick.
He'll resent being kept off.
He wants me on it anyway.
What will happen to the men on this list ?
Good day Marek, you know about the cable ?
I hear folk talk about it.
You didn't hear anything last night ?
I sleep. Not hear noise.
But when the Germans started to run amok ?
Well then ?
You know I always got the dunce cap too.
It's not serious.
Yes it is serious...
When Papa finds out he'll give me a walloping.
Well, all you have to do is not tell him.
I thought policemen say you
always have to tell the truth !
In general yes, but there are exceptions.
So what have you done to earn the dunce cap
on the first day at school ?
I stole some of the quince jam.
Right. Well, true enough, that's serious.
But it wasn't my fault. I was hungry.
And there was only a small piece for two.
That's also not fair.
A little bit for two on the first day of school ?
There were supposed to be thieves last night,
but I'm sure its lies.
Please.
It's about the theft last night ?
No. no, no. These gentlemen are from the Academy.
It's about the aircraft incident.
Sorry to arrive unannounced.
We sent you a letter...
....but with the mail just now...
Good. Go on. We can set up here.
Don't worry, I'll stay with you.
Ah, you plan to attend the interview ?
With respect it's the rule Monsieur l'Inspecteur.
The head has the right to assist a teacher
in all disciplinary proceedings.
Yes. One can, one can. But not 'One Must'.
That said, it's not inappropriate that you
be here, because if one thinks about it...
...all that Mademoiselle Borderie did on June 12th,
she did under your authority. Didn't she ?
Mademoiselle, sit down here please.
I wasn't present on the morning of June 12th.
And unaware. For as you know there wasn't
an official request to take the children out.
Ah, yes. You weren't present. Where were you then ?
At Besançon where the Rector was giving me
the Academic Medal.
You are Jewish, Madame Morhange, I believe ?
Yes.
I don't see the connection.
Oh, it's context.
Its part of the context. Context
is important in human affairs.
Plato even said at a feast,
that it's the essence of things.
Oh, I'm not an expert on Plato.
No, of course, I can imagine.
You prefer Spinoza, perhaps ?
I would like a moment. It's the Commissaire of Police.
Tell me, did you have a burglary last night ?
Oh, yes. We were robbed of bits and pieces.
I was going to tell you about it later...
Can it wait ?
No.
But I wont keep you long.
Can we suspend things a moment,
while I accompany the Commissaire ?
Oh yes. Go on, don't worry.
Good.
It was the Canteen worker who
discovered it this morning.
Apparently he's missing a ham and half,...
....some honey and quince jam.
Well that's annoying but not the end of the world.
Right, but nevertheless
a ham and a half...right now !
You sleep up there, do you ?
Well yes, with the young teacher.
With the Germans in occupation
alongside it's a real war.
Can I question her, just a minute.
Are you kidding. She's already being taken apart
by two morons from the Academy...
Good. In any case she heard and saw nothing.
Just a moment there Madame.
In my view the thief came in here...
... and left by the window using the cable,
and then crashed down.
Anyway, it's clearly a robbery and not sabotage.
Let's hope the Fritz are satisfied with that.
You'd like so much to satisfy them ?
We can't all do what we like, you know.
On reflection, have you come to terms with
your responsibility for the children's deaths ?
I don't know, Monsieur.
What do you mean, you don't know ?
If... if we had stayed in class...
... a bomb could have fallen on the school.
At Champeix, a bomb fell squarely on the class.
The teacher and seven children were killed.
This is incredible !
You talk about what could have happened.
We are talking about what did happen.
You went out with the children.
A plane came. They were killed.
Yes...
You don't understand that if you hadn't gone
out that day the children would be alive ?
Yes.
It's behaviour like this that
has got us where we are today.
Thinking that everything is allowed.
Thinking that one can...
Rules are made to be followed, Mademoiselle.
Because of your whim, France has lost
two of its children.
Then, you're not solely responsible, agreed...
... however I would really like to hear you,
acknowledge your fault.
Excuse me, I didn't hear you.
I am responsible.. it's my fault.
My God...
Sign here.
Name and surname, if you please.
Well then, I believe we're finished.
I understood that we'd suspended the session.
Ah. The Regulations say nothing about what
to do when the Headmistress absents herself.
And then Mademoiselle Borderie,
spoke to us spontaneously...
... its better for her anyway.
Madame Morhange.
When will we know the follow-up to this matter ?
Quickly, I think.
Finally, I hardly see how one can let someone teach,
who can't see the difference between...
.....the possible and reality.
How could you have signed the document.
Couldn't you have waited until I returned ?
But it's true. I am responsible. It's true.
No ! That's not the issue.
These men were not here...
... they were not here to find the truth.
They were here to...
In these cases you should never sign anything.
You're really in trouble now.
Shit !
...et..... trois....... kinder....           Children.....        Children !
Hannes, Rupert and Alma
I have one: Marceau.
Marceau. Only one son ?
Can I talk to her ? I work with her.
Work...?
Yes
Only speak, eh....       Speak....
I can't cross but he says that I can come up to here.
What's happening ?
Ah, I have a problem with my Ausweis.
I have bad news, Marie.
It's Lorrain.
Yes.
I'm sorry.
They don't even say what happened.
Behind the barrier !
Don't cross the Line.
She just lost her husband, so shut up.
I'm going to tell the kids.
Madame, go back. Quickly !
I'll return tomorrow.
I'm with you.
I'm thinking of you.
Her husband was killed in the war.
Ah. ... the war.   Not Good.
Excuse me.
We think that that a thief got into the school pantry.
Climbing down the facade...
...the thief, by chance pulled down the military cable.
The cable ran near the window...
... he used it like a rope.
You really think that a burglar picked a place
where 20 German soldiers were sleeping !
Perhaps he didn't know. It's got 'School'
written on the wall.
... not German Barracks.
Listen Kommandant, if, as we believe,
it's really a case of food theft...
...the thief isn't from round here, because
he didn't know the school had become a barracks.
He's long gone now. We'll not catch him.
That's not my problem.
Meanwhile, I want the list of 20 names
that I asked for this morning.
What is this list for Kommandant ?
They're the names of volunteers who are accountable
for the nightly guarding of military cables.
Along the railways, because that's
where saboteurs are found.
Understand, if another sabotage takes place
they'll be held responsible.
You can't ask these men to be out all night.
They work.
A nightly guard until the saboteur's arrest.
The first guard will be tonight.
Daniel Larcher, Henri de Kervern.
I didn't think that you would
put yourself on the list.
What news ?
There's an important Comrade who wants to see you.
Where ?
At Les Essarts.
It's on the other side of the Line.
Comrade, it's a Party Order.
The Comrade has taken risks to meet with you.
The Party is counting on you.
How am I going to cross the Line
without an Ausweis?
You know the old railway tunnel at Poligny?
There's a 20 metre passage that leads to
the Unoccupied Zone.
It's not guarded at night,
neither one end nor the other.
You come back next night, it's a piece of cake.
But that means leaving during the curfew...
And, I remind you, I have a kid....
....that my wife is ill in bed.
We all have wives and kids Comrade.
Lots of Comrades are in prison.
What time is the meeting ?
Nine o'clock in front of the Great Oak Calvaire.
The Comrade will call himself Edmond.
You will call yourself Paul.
Ask him for a light. He'll reply that he doesn't
smoke because it's bad for the throat.
Above all be on time.
Has Maman been sleeping a while ?
She was already asleep when I came home from school.
What are you doing there ?
I'm drawing lines for writing practice.
For tomorrow.
Gustave, keep busy a while.
This is crap.
Max gave me a message.
I have to meet a Comrade
on the other side of the Line tonight.
I shall be away all tomorrow.
If you must, you must !
He says it's an important Comrade.
Perhaps he has news from the Federation.
Don't jump on the bed, Gustave.
How was school today ?
Good, good, our pal, little Louis,
stole some quince jam.
He even had to wear the dunce's cap.
You didn't tell on him, at least ?
No !
Well that's good.
It's not nice to steal but it's worse to squeal.
Never forget that.
Listen. I have something important to tell you.
This evening I have to go out.
You're going to be alone with Maman.
But you're not allowed to go out at night.
I have an important errand to do.
An errand that you shouldn't talk about to anyone.
Not to your pals nor your teacher. Understand ?
If you talk of it, something bad could happen to us.
Please, Messieurs.
I little quiet please.
Messieurs there will be four groups,
each with two German soldiers.
Armed ?
Of course not.
And what do we do if we see something
or someone ? What do we do ?
Well....
You come to see me or Inspecteur Marchetti.
There are four groups. We'll be separated
from each other. How will we communicate ?
Well if you see something you warn
the German soldiers, and then that's it.
Please. Please.
Anyway you won't see a saboteur,
because there won't be any sabotage.
It's useless. It's done especially to
humiliate us, and make us feel they're the masters.
Don't fall into the mistake of
bickering about the details.
Please. Please. Please !
Are there to be sleep breaks,
so we're not all washed out ?
No, von Ritter was categorical. No-one sleeps.
The guards will be watching us.
There's not only bad news !
There's not only bad news ! The Préfecture
and Sous-Préfecture have decided to compensate us.
At a rate of seven francs a night.
Well that's something.
Go on then. Leave in a quarter of an hour.
Let's go, Messieurs.
It's still incredible to be forced
to mount guard like squaddies.
Squaddies without guns...
Reminds me of my youth.
You were really in the Great War ?
And was it as...    as hard as everyone says ?
Oh during the War I wasn't on guard duty,
I was in a medical unit.
No. That was earlier. During my Military
Service in Brittany in 1913.
By the way, did you inform Marie Germain,
in spite of the invalidity of Ausweis?
Yes.
And about an Ausweis, can you get me one?
With my sub-contractors it would
definitely be more convenient.
No. Von Ritter is absolutely furious
about the cable.
I suppose he had his chain jerked by his superiors.
In any case it's better for now to do nothing,
apart from catching our thief.
In fact I may have a means of getting Ausweis.
I'd like to know what you think of it.
Von Ritter has suggested
that I work for the Kommandantur.
He needs wood to extend the barracks
at the boys' school.
Right, that would solve the Ausweiss question.
What do you think ?
Of what ?
Of von Ritter's proposal.
I'm sure that the Sous-Préfet will like it.
And you ?
You think that all this delights me ?
It must be done well.
We lost the war. We have to try and win the peace.
Moreover the instructions of the Préfecture
are very clear. The economy must be restored.
And as of now, only the Fritz' have money...
Halt, Halt, Halt !
Halt. Don't move !
What do we do ?
Who is this clown ?
He's a guy who wants to cross the Line.
Where did you come from ?
I'm walking. Don't I have the right to walk ?
No, not a dead of night. Go on. On your knees.
Saboteur ! Just a guy who wants to cross the Line.
Go on. Throw him in the hole. Get his life history.
No-one moves before 8 in the morning.
I'm taking him to the Commissariat de Police.
I'm the Commissaire.
Good. You keep him. He can keep you company.
He'll keep you busy.
I've had enough. Shit !
Boss ? Commissaire ?
De Kervern ?
What's wrong with you ?
He's had this problem for a long time.
Angina, he needs Vilcanol.
We need to take him to my office.
Herr Hauptmann !    Dont move !
But this man is having a heart attack. He may die.
He told you... Police ! French Police, in the Name of God !
Don't move !
Call your Kommandant.
De Kervern ?
We're going OK. That's enough. Stand up.
My car is back there.
Don't move !
Do you know what you're doing ?
He won't shoot at Police.
Herr Hauptmann ! Don't move !
I'm going to shoot.
Shit !
What's going on ?
He's had a heart attack. Your husband says
that he needs Vilcanol tablets.
Get him into the lounge. And Daniel ?
He stayed with the others.
Don't worry. All is well.
I really chose a good time. Huh ?
I'm sorry to bother you.
No. You're absolutely not bothering me.
Lie down and try to sleep a little.
I am going to look for capsules.
Very well.
Thank you.
Here.
Take this.
Thank you.  I can rest a little, OK,
but certainly not sleep.
I'll have to go back. Do you think you can manage ?
Yes, of course.
Relax and breathe, OK ?
I'll be back.
Good. Right away.
I know it's a bad time, but I want to thank you.
For what... ?
Well that you agreed to give me lodging...
... but if my presence bothers you, say so.
I can always find something else.
There's a camp bed in the loft of the Commissariat.
No, not at all. I am quite happy for you to be here.
Very good.
Edmond ?
Good God, be more discreet!
You should be more punctual. I've waited an hour.
Do you live on German time Paul?
Here in the Unoccupied Zone we live
on French Time. It's 9 o'clock.
You shouldn't stay more than
two minutes at a rendez-vous.
You didn't give me the security phrase
about your throat.
Let's walk.
Do you have contact with the Federation ?
Or the Leadership ?
Why ?
I don't know...
... for the evolution of the Party Line.
I've had nothing since June.
It hasn't changed.
We hold to the Line of the Nazi-Soviet Pact.
Comrade Stalin knows what he's doing.
It's on Pétain and Laval that
we need to focus our attacks.
Pétain, Laval, the 200 Families...
The plutocrats of London and Vichy.
We don't say anything about the Germans ?
The Germans ...  are a typical false problem.
The enemy is the Nazi, not the German.
Most German soldiers are not Nazis.
They are Workers in uniform, Paul.
Workers like us.
Listen, I understand of course, but...
... but to recruit people with this Line
is simply impossible.
Why ?
Because in the Occupied Zone the
Germans are the problem, not Pétain.
Requisitions, the curfew, harassment. It's the Germans.
Paul, you're questioning the Party Line !
Excuse me.
I've to tell you that you've been named
political head of the Villeneuve sector.
Recruit Comrades, and spread the Party Line.
Behind the Calvaire, under some stones,you'll
find 100 papers to distribute as soon as possible.
Get on with it. For us it's gold.
Slide them under doors, and in letterboxes.
You've understand what the Party expects of you ?
Yes.
One last thing.
My boss may do work for the Germans.
That's a problem ?
If I stay in the company ?
On the contrary, I've told you
the Germans are not the enemy.
And if that changes... we won't be unhappy
to have Comrades in place, working for them.
Good day, Sarah.
Monsieur.
Ah, make me something to eat.
....some wine, some cheese...
I'll go and see what I can find
but it won't be much, you know.
Did Marceau sleep well ?
No. He still has nightmares.
So, your night guard duty ?
Cruel !
By the way, de Kerven failed to complete it.
He had a heart attack.
Oh, poor man. Is he improving ?
Well, I hope so. He's a good guy.
Indeed, there's not much.
I do my best, Monsieur.
No, I don't blame you, Sarah.
How am I going to work after such a night.
My poor love !
The Germans really treat us like...
... like slaves.
Clémenceau was right, France is dead.
Well, I don't know, but I had
a curious proposition yesterday.
Kreiskommandant von Ritter offered me a deal.
.. and an important deal.
... which will bail out our bank accounts.
... beams and planks for the Boys' School.
He'll pay in francs ?
In Reichmarks.
Than accept. It's a windfall.
All the same !
What will people think ? Working for the Germans !
That you're lucky.
Tell your father. He doesn't like the Boches much.
Yes. But believe me he likes Reichmarks.
The exchange rate does nothing
for Franco-German friendship.
Good !... The problem is, that if I accept...
I'll have to go regularly to Berthier's.
I'll even need to send a guy there from time to time.
You could sleep at the farm. It's quite close.
Did you tell Marie about Lorrain?
Yes.
How did she react ?
Ah, not well. Obviously.
Oh, the poor thing.
Von Ritter didn't want to know.
The guard is on again for tonight.
What a misery !
What can we do ?
I don't know.
As for the thief....any trace ?
No.
You know. I'm a bit like you. I've hardly slept.
Yes of course.
Excuse me.
You were great last night.
What happened ?
Nothing. It's ... not important.
The Germans didn't want Commissaire de Kervern
taken away, when he had his attack...
... and Inspecteur Marchetti took him anyway.
In spite of being threatened by a soldier with a gun.
You know, in those moments you don't think.
Up already ?
Do you feel better ?
All somersaults. I was wakened
by hunger. May I ?
Yes. Of course. Sit down.
Maria, a plate for the Commissaire.
I will examine you in a moment.
You don't look too bad.
Any news ?
No. Nothing.
What's going to be done with
the guy we arrested last night ?
We'll charge him with assault and battery.
That ham there....
It's not good ?
Certainly. Yes... but...
... where did you get it ?
You'll have to ask our magician. Maria ?
The ham ?
It came from Fernandez.
No. No. Fernandez hasn't had any since the Spring.
So, Maria, tell us where the ham came from.
I'm sorry Monsieur. It came from
Clémentine, the clothes mender.
Monsieur Marek, the school handyman, sold it to her.
Bring it here, please.
Thank you.
This is the Commissary mark.
It's the ham that was stolen
from the school the other night.
You know the black market is forbidden ?
Not black market. Just help each other.
You have a funny way of helping each other !
Ten times the official price.
Official price for shops.
But in shop, no ham.
Stop it Marek, we know the song, words and music.
Where did you get the ham ?
I... it mine.
You want us to believe that you have the money
to buy a ham and a half.
Not buy. Is gift.
Ah good. And who gave you this present ?
Monsieur Fournier, teacher.
Do work for him at school and give ham.
Marek is so intelligent!
Making the dead speak.
When was that ?
In month May.
That's a shame because there's a stamp on this ham...
... it was made in August.
Marek, you're going to have to stop
screwing us around, huh.
One, lying to the Police;
Two, theft; Three, black market.
This is starting to be a big deal.
No stolen. Found, no stolen !
Found then ... where ?
That night, hear noise.
Commotion. I go window. See run.
Throw bag, yellow. And I get ham.
Who was this man ?
Leave, run, happen. Germans come. Not see.
Good. I'll call Monsieur le Maire.
No. Not stolen, found.
Tell him we've got the thief.
The honey and the quince jam, Marek ?
Honey, I keep.
Not quince jam.
Honey, ham...
Good. Then it's him ?
You're sure of it ?
He sold the ham on the black market, he was
on the scene because he sleeps in the school.
You don't agree, or what ?
He admits the ham and honey but not the quince jam.
So a guy who admits stealing the big thing but not the
little ones, I've never seen that in all my career.
All the same, you know, criminal logic...
Good, lets accept that he stole the ham.
But Marek lives there...
Why does he go out by the window ?
Why the acrobatics ?
He had only to pinch the ham, take it to where
he sleeps and then leave with it a little later.
I don't know. He could have been surprised
in the pantry. He would have panicked.
I don't believe it.
What's more he's too old to climb down the cable.
No. It's someone else who did the robbery,
who panicked when the Germans arrived,
and abandoned the ham there.
Marek arrived. He found the ham. There you go !
Good. In any case the black market case is established...
... and accessory to the theft.
Good.
Monsieur le Maire, what do we do ?
We can't miss a chance of calming down the Germans.
In any case Marek has lied to the Police.
He's worked the black market. Yes.
He's an accessory to robbery.
Technically. Finally there's concealment.
It's for the judge to decide his fate, not us...
I'm going to warn the Sous-Préfet
that we've found one of those responsible
for the damage to the cable.
Will you call Justice at Besançon ?
Monsieur le Sous-Préfet, please.
The Mayor of Villeneuve.
I am very satisfied with this arrangement.
Don't be surprised. There will have to be
an investigation by our Security Service...
They'll want the names of your employees
and a plan of the factory. It's routine.
Yes, I understand.
Respect for the schedule is very important.
German insistence on punctuality is not a myth.
I'll try to supply you with petrol
for the duration of the work.
But I promise nothing.
Finally a permanent priority Ausweiss...
With that you can cross the Line
as many times as necessary.
Thank you.
Hauptmann !
Hello ? Ah my dear Servier !
You've found the saboteur.
Bravo !
The Sous-Préfet says von Ritter is delighted.
He thinks there'll be no more
guarding, from tonight on.
You could say that we were scared, eh ?
And Marek ? What will he get ?
Oh, a few months.
Black market !
I've come to take charge of the prisoner, Marek Dutchya,
who's sought by the German Army for sabotage.
But ... this has to be an error.
This man has been arrested by the French Police...
He should be judged by French Justice.
I have a formal order to take charge of this man.
An order signed by Kreiskommandant Helmut von Ritter.
I have to execute the order.
It's a violation of the Armistice Convention.
Check with your superiors.
We are not going to let this happen !
I'll call the Sous-Préfet again.
Monsieur le Sous-Préfet, please.
The Mayor of Villeneuve.
Servier, it's Larcher again.
We've a problem. German soldiers are here,
wanting to take the ham thief away.
He's ours !
We've a problem. German soldiers are here,
wanting to take the ham thief away.
He's ours !
The Germans want him. We're not going to
stand on ceremony, he's a black marketeer,
a thief, and what's more, a foreigner.
I don't see what the problem is.
It's a matter of principle. Our Police have
arrested him to bring him before French justice.
The French State upholds the Rule of Law.
There's only one principle that counts, to be
willing to look after our citizen's interests.
Von Ritter tells me the parcel issue can be sorted out.
As for the curfew, it goes back to 20:00h.
... we're not going to piss them off
for a shady foreigner !
Anyway, we haven't a choice.
Go ahead.
We haven't a choice.
Open.
Marek.
Why ?     Eh ?.
It not fair ! Not thief.
Not thief.
Not steal !
Why do that ?
De Kervern.
Yes, one moment.
Monsieur le Maire.
It's for you.
Larcher.
What ?
Oh, My God.
I'll be there right away.
A family emergency.
In spite of the circumstances,
I want to thank you for your work.
It went pretty well.
Yes, except for Marek.
And the other one. What should we do ?
Remand him ?
What's that ?
It's paper.
Give it to me.
Get about your business ..... before they shoot you.
Go !
Was it you who got the Priest here ?
She was born a Catholic.
Go away.
You go away too.
My condolences, Marcel.
If you need anything whatever...
Yes. Go away !
You said that if I said anything,
something bad would happen...
... but I never said anything, Papa.
I never said anything.